Quazi Irfan

Data Scientist | Statistician | Data Analyst | Data Engineer

quazirfan@gmail.com; Mobile 386 334 4792

🔾 github.com/quazi-irfan **in** linkedin.com/in/quazi-irfan 🖹 StackOverflow/quazi-irfan 🗷 medium.com/@quazirfan

Summary: Recent grad in Statistics and Computer Science bringing in uncommon combination of competitive programming skill, theoretical understanding of fundamental data analysis algorithms, and research experience with desire to join high performing team and take on ownership of complex business problems with minimal supervision.

WORK EXPERIENCES

• Data Engineer at Genus(ABS Global), Madison, WI

11/2022 - Current

- Developed deep understanding of the organization and extracted business-critical data from large disorganized dataset, identified potential inconsistencies, and prepared tables for downstream analysis
- Built multiple data transformation pipelines using **DBT** and **SQL** and deployed them in production
- Developed and maintained multiple Metabase dashboards to keep stakeholders up to date
- Software Engineer(at Query.AI, Brookings, SD

01/2022 - 10/2022

- Implemented Python modules to extract data from REST endpoints and validated using PyTest unit testing
- Improved task queue(Celery) performance by 80% using Python green threads of web app running on Docker(AWS)
- Researcher & Teaching Assistant at South Dakota State University, Brookings, SD

09/2018 - 12/2021

- Researched drift compensation using **linear regression** to estimate displacement by double integrating acceleration signal obtained from inertial measurement sensor
- Researched signal processing algorithm(FIR and IIR) to smooth acceleration signal and different numerical integration techniques to integrate discrete time signal
- Built Java Swing application to draw obstacle map and visualized breadth-first search pathfinding algorithm \mathbf{Q}
- Co-developed R and SAS programming course and contributed to textbook 'Learn R through examples'
- Fixed logical and library dependency bugs by decompiling Java binary used for data analysis
- Decreased grading time by 90% by developing automation scripts to grade x86 assembly programs
- Implemented string matching algorithm (Jaro-Winkler) algorithm to detect similar assignment submissions ()

Data Analysis & Programming Projects

- Applied Multiple Linear regression and feature selection methods to correctly identify useful predictors
- Improved **model prediction** accuracy and interpretability by addressing **multicollinearity** problem using Variation Inflation Factor, Ridge and LASSO
- Built classifier for **high dimensional fingerprint dataset** using dimension reduction technique (principal component analysis) and linear discriminate analysis
- Analyzed datasets using SQL and developed JavaFX app that dynamically generates UI from DB metadata
- Developed data visualization dashboard (web application) using Flask, Pandas and Plotly and deployed on Linux VM running on Google Compute Engine behind Nginx reverse proxy
- Researched 25 years of Particle Swarm Optimization and implemented vanilla PSO in Julia and Python O
- Implemented backtracking algorithm to calculate Schur's number Q
- Implemented Markov chain Monte Carlo sampler in R and C++ to compute posterior distribution 🔾
- Developed assembler for SIC-XE instruction set in Java 🔾
- Developed Ada to 16bit Intel 8086 compiler using recursive descent parser generating three address code Q
- Built 2d side-scrolling game using Java 2d featuring axis-aligned-bounding-box collision detection Ω
- Organized multiple ACM seminars on Git and Vim; Reported bugs on Unity3d and IntellijIDEA

EDUCATION & SKILLS

- MS Statistics (Fall '21) and BS Computer Science (Summer '18) from South Dakota State University
- Skills: Python(Numpy, Flask, Matplotlib, sklearn, statsmodels, Plotly, Pytest), R, Java, SQL(PostgreSQL), Redis, Bash, Linux, HTML/CSS, Javascript, REST, Git, Github, Vim, Docker, Algorithm analysis, Relational database, Linear Algebra, Statistical Inference and Modeling(Regression and Multivariate Analysis), Bayesian Statistics

Publications & Awards

- Building exoskeleton glove on virtual reality platform Irfan, Q., Jensen, C., Ni, Z. & Hietpas, S., 2018 IEEE EIT
 - Bennett Fellowship recipient(\$5,000) to build game and motor-driven VR gloves to track finger movement and send haptic feedback when the real finger interacts with a virtual object(Research Blog on Medium)
- Inertia Measurement Unit-Based Displacement Estimation via Velocity Drift Compensation Using Ordinary Least Squares Method Irfan, Q., Ciarcia, M. and Hatfield, G., 2022 IEEE EIT

REFERENCES

• Dr. George Hamer, Ph.D.

Assistant Department Head

Associate Professor

Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department

South Dakota State University

SECS 121

Brookings, S.D. 57007

605 - 688 - 5721

George.Hamer@sdstate.edu

(Instructor in CSC-314 Assembly Language, CSC-354 Systems Programming and CSC-446 Compiler Construction)

• Jason Werpy

Instructor

Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department

South Dakota State University

SECS 165

Brookings, S.D. 57007

605-690-3576

jason.werpy@sdstate.edu

jason.werpy@us.kbr.com

(Instructor in CSC 484 Database, Undergraduate research proposal supervisor)

• Dr. Gary Hatfield, Ph.D.

Associate Professor

Mathematics & Statistics Department

South Dakota State University

Architecture, Math & Engineering Building 256

Math & Statistics-Box 2225

University Station

Brookings, SD 57007

605-688-5846

gary.hatfield@sdstate.edu

(Graduate research advisor and instructor in Stochastic process and Probabilistic robotics course)

• Dr. Marco Ciarcia, Ph.D.

Assistant Professor

Department of Mechanical Engineering

South Dakota State University

Crothers Engineering Hall - Office 210

Mechanical Engineering-Box 2219

University Station

Brookings, SD 57007

605 - 688 - 5908

Marco.Ciarcia@sdstate.edu

(Graduate research advisor)